<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sitrism on Syntrizm - politico-philosophical concept and model of state organization based on the balance of three sources of power: human institutions, artificial intelligence, and direct democracy</title><link>https://mmortall.github.io/blogs-Mind-Journal/tags/sitrism/</link><description>Recent content in Sitrism on Syntrizm - politico-philosophical concept and model of state organization based on the balance of three sources of power: human institutions, artificial intelligence, and direct democracy</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Sergii Taraban</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 10:23:45 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mmortall.github.io/blogs-Mind-Journal/tags/sitrism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>About the essence of any political system</title><link>https://mmortall.github.io/blogs-Mind-Journal/posts/en/about-the-essence-of-any-political-system/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 10:23:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mmortall.github.io/blogs-Mind-Journal/posts/en/about-the-essence-of-any-political-system/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The essence of any system is to resolve the conflict between freedom and order.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we move away from labels like &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;democracy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;dictatorship&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;technocracy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, there are always two fundamental issues at the heart of any political system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="1-management-issue"&gt;1. &lt;strong&gt;Management Issue&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to organize decision-making in a large society?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who has the right to determine the &amp;ldquo;course&amp;rdquo; - the people, elites, experts, algorithms?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to balance between &lt;strong&gt;efficiency&lt;/strong&gt; (quick, coordinated decisions) and &lt;strong&gt;legitimacy&lt;/strong&gt; (so that the majority accepts them as fair)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why contemporary research speaks not so much of &amp;ldquo;forms of government&amp;rdquo; as of &lt;strong&gt;governance&lt;/strong&gt; - a process of governance that can be state, corporate, networked, algorithmic.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>